{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Lewis Keseberg, a member of this group, was nearly lynched after being found with over $200 and a pistol belonging to this group’s namesake. James Reed attempted to rescue this group, which attempted to cross the Hastings Cutoff after a late departure from Independence, Missouri. For ten points, name this group of pioneers that led a doomed 1846 overland expedition to California that famously resulted in cannibalism.",
      "answer": "Donner Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the alleged first game of this sport, one team dressed in handkerchiefs and turbans to distinguish themselves from the other team, and Rutgers beat Princeton 6 to 4. Lorin Deland invented this sport’s “flying wedge” play, which was banned in 1894. In 1905, Teddy Roosevelt invited leaders of this sport to the White House to discuss its poor safety record; shortly after, rules changes supported by John Heisman made the forward pass legal. For ten points, name this sport in which teams once earned four points for a touchdown.",
      "answer": "American football"
    },
    {
      "question": "A “Great” ruler with this name negotiated with Basil II in order to marry his daughter Anna; that prince of Novgorod witht his name began the process of Christianizing the Kievan Rus after being impressed by a trip to Constantinople. A modern leader with this first name alternated terms as president of his country with Dmitry Medvedev and controversially annexed the Crimea in 2014. For ten points, give this first name of the current President of Russia.",
      "answer": [
        "Vladimir",
        "Vladimir the Great",
        "Vladimir Putin after “modern” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Eleutherian Gunpowder Mills were built in this state by a Frenchman. An asthmatic patriot from this state rode through a rainstorm to reach the Continental Congress. This state’s city of Lewes was the site of the Swedish colony of Fort Christina. The company that would become Du Pont is headquartered in this state, which Caesar Rodney represented at the Continental Congress. The first state to ratify the US Constitution was, for ten points, what state with capital Dover?",
      "answer": "Delaware"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country renamed its capital after its then-dictator in the 1930s and built a massive cross-shaped monument to Christopher Columbus for the 500th anniversary of his landing in the Americas. When the only country that borders this country was led by Stenio Vincent, Vincent was too weak to ask for compensation after this country’s troops committed the Parsley Massacre. For ten points, name this country in which President Rafael Trujillo killed Creole-speaking migrants from neighboring Haiti.",
      "answer": "Dominican Republic"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frederick the Great gave this man the nickname “Cyclops,” in reference to his worsening vision in one eye; later, this man remarked “Now I will have fewer distractions,” upon losing sight in both eyes. The publication of this man’s Letters to a German Princess was supported by Catherine the Great. This thinker developed basic graph theory to conclude that no path could cross each of the seven bridges of Konigsberg only once. For ten points, name this Swiss mathematician, the namesake of the constant e.",
      "answer": "Leonhard Euler , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "A photograph taken by Yevgeny Khaldei in this city was edited to prevent accusations of looting and depicts a man waving a Soviet flag above a destroyed building. A structure in this city contains the mural “My God, Help Me to Survive This Deadly Love;” that structure was once crossed at Checkpoint Charlie. In a 1963 visit, John F. Kennedy said he was a citizen of, for ten points, what European city that was divided by a namesake wall during the Cold War?",
      "answer": [
        "Berlin",
        "West Berlin and/or East Berlin after “mural” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s tallest commercial building is One Franklin Square, which was granted an exemption to the 1910 Height of Buildings Act and reaches 210 feet. In 2017, stained glass windows commemorating Robert E. Lee and Stonewall Jackson were removed from this city’s third tallest building, the National Cathedral. For ten points, name this city where every building is at least 200 feet shorter than a 555-foot monument to the first President of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington D.C.",
        "DC",
        "District of Columbia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Alonso de Avellaneda wrote an unauthorized sequel to this novel, causing its author to rush its second volume to completion ten years after its first volume appeared. The tale of a captive in the 39th chapter of this novel was based on its author’s kidnapping by pirates and enslavement by the Moors. This novel’s title character is bored of his life in La Mancha, causing him to take a noble name and become a knight. For ten points, name this novel by Miguel de Cervantes.",
      "answer": "Don Quixote"
    },
    {
      "question": "This war was the subject of a controversy in which members of the 1st Mechanized Infantry Division used bulldozers to clear out fortified lines by burying enemy troops alive. This war’s losing side attempted to retreat through Highway 80, the so-called “Highway of Death.” Norman Schwarzkopf was able to win this war within sixty days of the initial invasion of Kuwait. For ten points, name this war in which George H.W. Bush authorized Operation Desert Storm against Saddam Hussein’s Iraqi forces.",
      "answer": [
        "Persian Gulf War",
        "First Gulf War",
        "First Iraq War",
        "do not"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader’s regime promoted the Stakhanovite movement and labeled enemies as wreckers. As opposed to an opponent’s idea of “permanent revolution,” this ruler promoted “socialism in one country.” This man frequently purged Old Bolsheviks in show trials and eventually had Ramon Mercador murder his rival, Leon Trotsky. For ten points, name this Soviet dictator who succeeded Vladimir Lenin and ruled during World War II.",
        "answer": "Joseph Stalin or Josef Dzhugashvili"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the time of his death, Leon Trotsky was exiled to this country, where he lived for a time with Diego Rivera.",
        "answer": "Mexico"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This material was used to make the death mask of Agamemnon, which Heinrich Schliemann found in 1876. This material, which is heavily used in cloaks in a painting of two lovers on a cliff by Gustav Klimt, was used with ivory to create chryselephantine sculptures. The outermost funerary mask of King Tutankhamen was plated in this material, whose “leaf” is often used in art. Alchemists often sought to create, for ten points, what metal that makes up electrum coins with silver?",
        "answer": "gold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Heinrich Schliemann found the mask of Agamemnon while excavating this ancient Greek archaeological site. This site south of Corinth names an era of Greek history.",
        "answer": [
          "Mycenae",
          "word forms, like Mycenaean Era"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1979, special forces from this European country converted to Islam so they could participate in lifting the Grand Mosque Siege in Mecca. Photographer Fernando Pereira was killed after this country ordered the destruction of the Rainbow Warrior. This country led an intervention against Tuareg rebels in its former colony of Mali in the early 2010s. For ten points, name this country that granted independence to Algeria after its police killed hundreds of Algerian protesters in Paris in 1961.",
        "answer": "France"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rainbow Warrior was a ship owned by this environmentalist organization; the French government ordered its sinking to prevent it from protesting French nuclear testing.",
        "answer": "Greenpeace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This First Lady invited members of the American Youth Congress to board at the White House when they were summoned to testify to Congress. Homeless miners in West Virginia inspired this woman to propose the planned community of Arthurdale. The UN Commission on Human Rights was chaired by this woman, who wrote its Universal Declaration on Human Rights and presented it in 1948. For ten points, name this longest-serving First Lady in American history, the wife of FDR.",
        "answer": "Eleanor Roosevelt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1939, Roosevelt resigned from this group after it refused to allow African-American singer Marian Anderson to give a concert at its Constitution Hall. This group restricts membership to women who are directly descended from pro-independence colonists.",
        "answer": "Daughters of the American Revolution or DAR"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Averroes’ works are primarily commentaries on this philosopher, who originated the syllogism form for logical deductions and postulated the state of “eudaemonia” as the goal of human life. In a book named after this man’s son Nichomachus, this man advocated finding the mean between extremes as virtuous. The Lyceum was founded by, for ten points, what ancient Greek philosopher who was a student of Plato?",
        "answer": "Aristotle"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aristotle originated this philosophical discipline with a work of the same name. It inquires into the nature of being and existence as such rather than the particular properties of things that exist.",
        "answer": "Metaphysics"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Prime Minister oversaw the passing of the Great Reform Bill of William IV. This husband of Kitty Pakenham rose to prominence fighting the Tipu Sultan’s kingdom of Mysore. The Battle of Wavre helped prevent Emmanuel Grouchy from attacking this man, who received assistance from Gebhard von Blucher in his most famous battle in a Belgian town. For ten points, name this “Iron Duke,” the English commander who fought Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo.",
        "answer": [
          "Arthur Wellesley, first Duke of Wellington",
          "either",
          "both underlined names"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before Waterloo, the Duke of Wellington’s English forces fought Napoleon in the Peninsular War on this European peninsula.",
        "answer": "Iberian Peninsula"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state includes a region once known as “No Man’s Land” whose southern border is on the 36-30 latitude line. A proposed state named Sequoyah was rejected in favor of the proposal that created this state. The Treaty of New Echota provided land in what is now this state in exchange for land in Georgia for the Cherokee. Under Jackson and van Buren, the Cherokee were forcibly marched to this state in the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this modern-day state that incorporates the former Indian Territory.",
        "answer": "Oklahoma"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Oklahoma panhandle exists because Texas gave up its land north of 36-30 as part of a compromise passed in this year. This compromise also banned slavery north of that latitude and admitted California to the Union.",
        "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to legend, the losing side in this battle goaded the victors by sending them three tennis balls when they asked for gold. The winning side in this battle was forced to kill all its prisoners after an enemy raid on their baggage train. During this battle, wooden stakes driven into muddy ground rendered the losing side’s heavy cavalry useless. For ten points, name this battle fought on St. Crispin’s Day, 1415, in which the longbow secured an overwhelming English victory against France in the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The English engaged the French at Agincourt while trying to reach Calais [ca-LAY], a city they controlled on the French shores of this body of water across from Dover.",
        "answer": "English Channel"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Socialism in the US",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Democratic Socialist who represents Vermont in the US Senate and ran for President in 2016.",
          "answer": "Bernard “Bernie” Sanders"
        },
        {
          "question": "primary.",
          "answer": [
            "New York City",
            "NYC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Blind and deaf woman who became a socialist activist after visiting a sweatshop.",
          "answer": "Helen Keller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sleeping car company against which socialists organized an 1894 strike in Illinois.",
          "answer": [
            "Pullman Car Company",
            "Pullman Strike"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Election year in which the Socialist candidate finished fourth behind Woodrow Wilson, William Howard Taft, and Theodore Roosevelt.",
          "answer": "1912 presidential election"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aforementioned socialist who also campaigned in the 1920 election, but from a prison cell.",
          "answer": "Eugene V. Debs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Case in which the “clear and present danger” doctrine was created to uphold the conviction of a Socialist antiwar organizer",
          "answer": "Schenck v. United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where “gas and water socialist” Victor Berger was elected to Congress in the early 20th century.",
          "answer": "Milwaukee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Switzerland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Swiss military policy since 1815, explaining why it was not purposely bombed in either World War.",
          "answer": [
            "neutrality",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Swiss city that hosted multiple conventions that established the rights of the wounded and civilians in wartime.",
          "answer": "Geneva"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious leader protected by the Swiss Guard in the Vatican City.",
          "answer": [
            "Pope",
            "Bishop of Rome",
            "Pope Francis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the 26 states that make up Switzerland, including Uri and Aargau.",
          "answer": "canton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swiss folk hero who legendarily shot an apple off his son’s head.",
          "answer": "William Tell or Guillaume Tell"
        },
        {
          "question": "French minister and believer in predestination who wrote Institutes of the Christian Religion before moving to Switzerland.",
          "answer": "John Calvin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protestant reformer who was based in Zurich and debated Martin Luther at the Marburg Colloquy.",
          "answer": "Ulrich Zwingli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of 16th century wars between Catholics and Protestants in which that reformer was killed.",
          "answer": "Kappel Wars India under British Rule Name the..."
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1664, British forces captured this city from the Dutch and renamed it to honor the original title of James II. A battle in this city started when forces under William Howe landed at Gravesend Bay and culminated with a daring (20 pts)",
        "night retreat by George Washington. Peter Minuit allegedly purchased a portion of this city from the (10 pts)",
        "Lenape natives for $24 worth of beads. This city, under the nearly created Constitution, was the first capital of the United States. For ten points, name this US city that contains Manhattan and the western tip of Long Island."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New York City or NYC",
        "New Amsterdam"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A holder of this position once ran for the Austrian presidency but was discovered to have been in the Wehrmacht during World War II. Kurt Waldheim held this position, as did a man whose (20 pts)",
        "plane was shot down during the Congo Crisis, Dag Hammarskjold [hammer-sk’yold]. A former holder of this position, (10 pts)",
        "Kofi Annan, died in August 2018, and Portugal’s Antonio Guterres succeeded Ban Ki-moon in this position in 2016. For ten points, name this position held by the chief administrator of the United Nations."
      ],
      "answer": "Secretary-General of the United Nations"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Note: two answers required. Disputes over a glacier between these two countries inspired the term oropolitics. A 1965 war between these two countries occurred after one of them launched the failed Operation Gibraltar and was ended by the Tashkent Declaration. These two countries were separated by the (20 pts)",
        "Radcliffe Line, which has been superseded by the Line of Control and Zero Point. The Siachen Glacier has been contested between these two countries, which have engaged in (10 pts)",
        "Cricket Diplomacy in order to reduce tensions. For ten points, name these two South Asian countries that have fought four wars since 1947, when they were partitioned from each other in their independence from Britain."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "India and Pakistan",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This site may have served as a memorial to the slain knights of Aurelius Ambrosius, a place described as the Giant’s Dance. 56 pits surrounding this site are known as the (20 pts)",
        "Aubrey holes and may have formed a bluestone circle. William Stukeley speculated that this site served as the center of (10 pts)",
        "Druid gatherings, and it was likely constructed by drawing from the Marlborough Downs quarry. For ten points, name this prehistoric site near Salisbury, England known for its standing rocks."
      ],
      "answer": "Stonehenge"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Eighteen of these works, including ones “for France,” “for Freedom,” and for “Airmen,” were commissioned by Cincinnati’s Eugene Goossens in 1942 to recognize the war effort. A speech by Henry (20 pts)",
        "Wallace inspired another of these musical works for Goossens, which was composed by Aaron (10 pts)",
        "Copland and premiered at income tax time to honor its subject, the “Common Man.” For ten points, name this type of musical piece, a usually short flourish for brass and percussion, commonly associated with the entrance of a royal leader."
      ],
      "answer": "fanfares"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Celeres served as the bodyguard of these people. One of these people was chosen to rule after lightning was seen around his head; his Servian Reforms allowed plebeians voting rights. The (20 pts)",
        "Vestal Virgins were brought out of Alba Longa by the second of these people, Numa Pompilius. The first of these people (10 pts)",
        "abducted the Sabine women, founded a city on the Palatine Hill, and may have killed his brother Remus. Lucius Tarquinius Superbus was the last man to hold, for ten points, what position as leader of an ancient city, first held by Romulus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kings of Rome",
        "Rex"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The institution of this festival was disputed by Quartodecimani, who instead celebrated it on the 14th of Nisan until the First Council of Nicaea set this festival to be exclusive of the (20 pts)",
        "Jewish calendar. Nevertheless, Computus for this moveable feast usually places it after the celebration of (10 pts)",
        "Passover, to preserve the commemoration of the Last Supper, while maintaining its position on a Sunday. For ten points, name this festival held after Holy Week, which celebrates the resurrection of Jesus."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Easter Sunday",
        "Pascha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One aerial assault during this battle left every attacker but George Gay dead. This battle, which was preceded by “Operation AL,” an attack on the Aleutians, was itself codenamed (20 pts)",
        "“AF” according to a code that was broken by the winning side. Indecision over arming aircraft with torpedoes or bombs cost (10 pts)",
        "Chuichi Nagumo victory in this battle, as that error led to the loss of four Japanese aircraft carriers. For ten points, name this turning point of the Pacific theater, a June 1942 naval battle fought over a namesake atoll."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Midway"
    }
  ]
}